import numpy as np
#create a 3*5 matrix with dtype as int...array(data_as_list,dtype)
a = np.array([[1, 2, 3, 4, 5], [6, 7, 8, 9, 10],[11, 12, 13, 14, 15]], int)
#print the [1st row, 1st column] element and [2nd row, 2nd column] element
print(a[[0,0],[1,1]])
#print the first row only...only one argument means row
print(a[0])
#print first column only..we select all rows and then choose only first elementof that row
print(a[:,0])          #print(a[0:,0]).....0: means all rows from first row
#print the length of a ..which means the number of individual list or rows
print(len(a))
#test if any value is in "a" using in statement
print(1 in a) #returns True as 1 is in "a"
#print the shape of the matrix
print(a.shape)
#create array using range() function
b=np.array(range(10),float)
print(b)     #b=np.array(range(10),float).reshape((5,2))
#reshape the array "b" using reshape(shape) method
print(b.reshape(5,2))  #creates a new reshaped array..does not modify original data itself
#copy() method can be used to create a new separate copy of an original data
c=a.copy()
print(c)    #copied a into c
#update or replace element in c
c[0,0]=0    #it replaces [1st row, 1st column] element by 0 in c but not in a
# list can be created from arrays using tolist() method
a=a.tolist()
#array can be converted into binary human non-readable string..tostring() method
s=b.tostring()
print(s)
#The fromstring function then allows an array to be created from this data later on.
#These routines are sometimes convenient for saving large amount of array data in files that can be read later on
b=np.frombuffer(s)    #frombuffer is preferred over fromstring
#one can fill an array with a single value using fill(value_to_fill) method
d=np.array([1,2,3],int)
d.fill(5.2)   #should provide same data type as above..if d.fill(5.2)..it does d.fill(5)
#transposed() method for a matrix
e=np.array([[.2,.3,.4],[.5,.6,.7]],dtype=float)
e=e.transpose()
#1D array of n-D can be created using flatten() method
f=e.flatten()
#Two or more arrays can be concatenated together using the np.concatenate(()) method
#with a tuple of the arrays to be joined:
a=np.array(range(4),dtype=float)
b=np.array(range(6),dtype=float)
c=np.array(range(2),dtype=float)
d=np.concatenate((a,b,c))
#If an array has more than one dimension, it is possible to specify the axis along which multiple arrays are concatenated.
#By default (without specifying the axis), NumPy concatenates along the first dimension:
a = np.array([[1, 2], [3, 4]], float)
b = np.array([[5, 6], [7,8]], float)
np.concatenate((a,b))    #by default this is same as saying np.concatenate((a,b),axis=0)
#lets concatenate along column which is axis=1
np.concatenate((a,b), axis=1)
#Finally, the dimensionality of an array can be increased using the newaxis constant in bracket notation:
a = np.array(range(3), int)
b=a[:,np.newaxis]     #this converets (3*1) shape to (1*3) shape
#we can do the other way as well    #The newaxis approach is convenient for generating the proper-dimensioned
c=b[np.newaxis,:]                   #arrays for vector and matrix mathematics.

##OTHER WAYS TO CREATE ARRAYS
#The arange function is similar to the range function but returns an array:
a=np.arange(5, dtype=float)
b=np.arange(1, 6, 2, dtype=int)  #1st one is where we start,2nd one is where we end, last one is the step size
#The functions zeros and ones create new arrays of specified dimensions filled with these values.
#These are perhaps the most commonly used functions to create new arrays:
a=np.ones((2,3), dtype=float) #creates 2*3 matrix filled with float 1.0
b=np.zeros(7, dtype=int)    #creates 1*7 matrix filled with integer 1
#The zeros_like and ones_like functions create a new array with the
#same dimensions and type of an existing one
a = np.array([[1, 2, 3], [4, 5, 6]], float)
b=np.zeros_like(a)    #creates a new matrix "b" exactly like "a" but filled with all zeros
c=np.ones_like(a)     #creates a new matrix "c" exactly like "a" but filled with all zeros
#To create an identity matrix of a given order(n)
I=np.identity(4, dtype=float)    #creates an identity matrix of order(4)
#The eye function returns matrices with ones along the kth diagonal:
np.eye(4, k=1, dtype=float)    #puts float 1.0 diagonally starting from second column as k=1 is specified

##ARRAY MATHEMATICS
a = np.array([1,2,3], float)
b = np.array([5,2,6], float)
a+b     #it adds two arrays like in matrix
a-b     #it subtracts two arrays like in matrix    #ERRORS ARE THROWN IF ARRAYS DO NOT MATCH IN SIZE
a*b     #it multiplies two arrays elementwise
a/b     #it divides two arrays elementwise
a%b     #it does modulo two arrays elementwise
a**b    #it takes element of "a" and raises corresponding element from"b" to its index
#For two-dimensional arrays, multiplication remains elementwise and does not correspond to matrix multiplication.
#There are special functions for matrix math that we will cover later.
a = np.array([[1,2], [3,4]], float)
b = np.array([[2,0], [1,3]], float)
a * b    #it multiplies first list to first list elementwise..output..[2,0],[3,12]
#However, arrays that do not match in the number of dimensions will be broadcasted by Python to perform mathematical operations.
#This often means that the smaller array will be repeated as necessary to perform the operation indicated. Consider the following:
a = np.array([[1, 2], [3, 4], [5, 6]], float)
b = np.array([-1, 3], float)
a + b     #here for each list in "a" the same list [-1,3] is used for the operation
#Sometimes, however, how we should broadcast is ambiguous. In these cases,
#we can use the newaxis constant to specify how we want to broadcast:
a = np.zeros((2,2), float)
b = np.array([-1., 3.], float)
a+b[np.newaxis,:]   #add "b" rowwise to "a" which is by default
a + b[:,np.newaxis]  #add "b" columnwise to "a"

#NumPy offers a large library of common mathematical functions that can be applied elementwise to arrays.
#Among these are the functions: abs, sign, sqrt, log, log10, exp, sin, cos, tan, arcsin, arccos,
#arctan, sinh, cosh, tanh, arcsinh, arccosh, and arctanh
a = np.array([1, 4, 9], float)
np.sqrt(a)
#The functions floor, ceil, and rint give the lower, upper, or nearest (rounded) integer:
a = np.array([1.1, 1.5, 1.9], float)
np.floor(a)    #rounds all numbers in list to lower integer..1.1 to 1
np.ceil(a)     #rounds all numbers in list to upper integer...1.1 to 2
np.rint(a)     #rounds to nearest integer...1.1 to 1 and 1.9 to 2
#remember np.pi and np.e

          #ARRAY ITERATION
#It is possible to iterate over arrays in a manner similar to that of lists:
a = np.array([1, 4, 5], int)
for x in a:
    print(x)
#For multidimensional arrays, iteration proceeds over the first axis such that each loop returns a subsection of the array:
a = np.array([[1, 2], [3, 4], [5, 6]], float)
for x in a:
    print (x)
#Multiple assignment can also be used with array iteration:
a = np.array([[1, 2], [3, 4], [5, 6]], float)
for (x, y) in a:
    print (x * y)

                             ##BASIC ARRAY OPERATIONS
#The items in an array can be summed or multiplied:
a = np.array([2, 4, 3], float)    
a.sum()    #sums all numbers in the list  or np.sum(a)
a.prod()    #multiplies all members in the list or np.prod(a)
a.mean()    # np.mean(a) and so on for all functions that follow
a.var()
a.min()      #min number in the list
a.max()      # max number in the list
#The argmin and argmax functions return the array indices of the minimum and maximum values:
a.argmin()    #np.argmin(a)
a.argmax()
#For multidimensional arrays, each of the functions thus far described can take an optional argument axis
#that will perform an operation along only the specified axis, placing the results in a return array:
a = np.array([[0, 2], [3, -1], [3, 5]], float)
a.mean(axis=0)
a.mean(axis=1)
a.min(axis=1)
a.max(axis=0)
#Lists, Arrays can be sorted
a = np.array([6, 2, 5, -1, 0], float)
sorted(a) #a.sort()...it sorts the data from min to max
#Values in an array can be "clipped" to be within a prespecified range.
#This is the same as applying min(max(x, minval), maxval) to each element x in an array.
a = np.array([6, 2, 5, -1, 0], float)
a.clip(0, 5)   # for example..for x=6..it does min(max(6,0),5)..which gives 5
#replaces the data in a within the prespecified range (0,5) w/ the method stated avove

#Unique elements can be extracted from an array: (it eliminates the repeated ones)
a = np.array([1, 1, 4, 5, 5, 5, 7], float)
np.unique(a)    #it gives output as [1.,4.,5.,7.] which are unique
#For two dimensional arrays, the diagonal can be extracted:
a = np.array([[1, 2], [3, 4]], float)
a.diagonal()     #output is [1.,4.]   #np.diagonal(a)

#Comparison Operators and Value Testing

#Boolean comparisons can be used to compare members elementwise on arrays of equal size.
#The return value is an array of Boolean True / False values:
a = np.array([1, 3, 0], float)
b = np.array([0, 3, 2], float)
c=a>b  #returns ([True,False,False],dtype=bool)
#Arrays can be compared to single values using broadcasting:
a = np.array([1, 3, 0], float)
a > 2       #returns ([True,False,True], dtype=bool)
#The any and all operators can be used to determine whether or not any or all elements of a Boolean array are true:
c = np.array([ True, False, False], bool)
any(c)    #its output as True cos at least one dtype is True
all(c)    #its output as False cos not all dtype is True
#Compound Boolean expressions can be applied to arrays on an element-by-element basis using special
#functions logical_and, logical_or, and logical_not.
a = np.array([1, 3, 0], float)
np.logical_and(a > 0, a < 3)   #outputs as ([True,False,False],dtype=bool)
b = np.array([True, False, True], bool)
np.logical_not(b)     #outputs as ([False, True, False],dtype=bool)
c = np.array([False, True, False], bool)
np.logical_or(b, c)    #outputs as ([True,True,True],dtype=bool)
#The where function forms a new array from two arrays of equivalent size using a Boolean filter
#to choose between elements of the two.Its basic syntax is where(boolarray, truearray, falsearray):
a = np.array([1, 3, 0], float)
b=np.where(a != 0, 1 / a, a)
#Broadcasting can also be used with the where function:
np.where(a > 0, 3, 2)      #which outputs as ([3,3,2]
#The nonzero function gives a tuple of indices of the nonzero values in an array.
#The number of items in the tuple equals the number of axes of the array:
a = np.array([[0, 1], [3, 0]], float)
a.nonzero()    #gives the index of non-zero elements...1 is indexed as [0,1] and 3 as [1,0]
#It is also possible to test whether or not values are NaN ("not a number") or finite:
a = np.array([1, np.NaN, np.Inf], float)
np.isnan(a)  #outputs bool as ([False,True,False],dtype=bool)
np.isfinite(a)  #outputs bool as ([True,False,False],dtype=bool)

#Array item selection and manipulation
#Unlike lists, however, arrays also permit selection using other arrays. That is, we can use array
#selectors to filter for specific subsets of elements of other arrays.
a = np.array([[6, 4], [5, 9]], float)
a>=6  #it outputs as ([True,False],[False,True])
b=a[a >= 6]     # it outputs as array([ 6., 9.])
a[np.logical_and(a > 5, a < 9)]  #outputs as ([6.])
#In addition to Boolean selection, it is possible to select using integer arrays.
a = np.array([2, 4, 6, 8], float)
b = np.array([0, 0, 1, 3, 2, 1], int)
a[b]    #it outputs as ([2.,2.,4.,8.,6.,4.]) same as a[[0, 0, 1, 3, 2, 1]]
#For multidimensional arrays, we have to send multiple one-dimensional integer arrays to the selection bracket, one for each axis.
a = np.array([[1, 4], [9, 16]], float)
b = np.array([0, 0, 1, 1, 0], int)
c = np.array([0, 1, 1, 1, 1], int)
a[b,c]   #its like saying a[[0,0],[0,1],....] which outputs as ([1.,4.,..])
#A special function take is also available to perform selection with integer arrays.
#This works in an identical manner as bracket selection:
a = np.array([2, 4, 6, 8], float)
b = np.array([0, 0, 1, 3, 2, 1], int)
a.take(b)   #same as a[[0,0,1,3,2,1]]..note that b is dtype=int otherwise we cannot pass as list index
#take also provides an axis argument, such that subsections of an multi-dimensional array can be taken across a given dimension.
a = np.array([[0, 1], [2, 3]], float)
b = np.array([0, 0, 1], int)
a.take(b, axis=0)   #its as saying (b=(0,0,1),axis=0) which is first row etc... which outputs ([0.,1.],(0.,1.],[2.,3.])??
a.take(b, axis=1)   #its as saying (b=(0,0,1),axis=1) which is first column etc..outputs ?
#The opposite of the take function is the put function, which will take values from a source array
#and place them at specified indices in the array calling put.
a = np.array([0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5], float)
b = np.array([9, 8, 7], float)
a.put([0, 3], b)    #put index value a[0]=9 from b & a[3]=8 from b which outputs as array([ 9., 1., 2., 8., 4., 5.])
#The source array will be repeated as necessary if not the same size:
a = np.array([0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5],float)
a.put([0, 3], 5) #this outputs as array([ 5.,1.,2.,5.,4.,5.]..repeats 5. as much needed


                                 #VECTOR AND MATRIX MATHEMATICS
#NumPy provides many functions for performing standard vector and matrix multiplication routines. To perform a dot product:
a = np.array([1, 2, 3], float)
b = np.array([0, 1, 1], float)
np.dot(a, b)
#The dot function also generalizes to matrix multiplication:
a = np.array([[0, 1], [2, 3]], float)
b = np.array([2, 3], float)
c = np.array([[1, 1], [4, 0]], float)
np.dot(b, a)   # which is [6.,11.]
np.dot(a, b)    #which is [3.,13.]  means ab and ba are not associative
np.dot(a, c)
np.dot(c, a)
#It is also possible to generate inner, outer, and cross products of matrices and vectors.
#For vectors, note that the inner product is equivalent to the dot product:
a = np.array([1, 4, 0], float)
b = np.array([2, 2, 1], float)
np.outer(a, b)
np.inner(a, b)
np.cross(a, b)
#NumPy also comes with a number of built-in routines for linear algebra calculations. These can be found in the sub-module linalg
a = np.array([[4, 2, 0], [9, 3, 7], [1, 2, 1]], float)
np.linalg.det(a)    #gives the det of matrix a
#One can find the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of a matrix:
vals, vecs = np.linalg.eig(a)   #gives eigenvalues and eigenvectors
#The inverse of a matrix can be found:
b = np.linalg.inv(a)
#check to make sure b is inverse of a as np.dot(a,b) is an identity matrix of order(3)
#Singular value decomposition aka svd (analogous to diagonalization of a nonsquare matrix) can also be performed:
a = np.array([[1, 3, 4], [5, 2, 3]], float)
U, s, Vh = np.linalg.svd(a)

                   #POLYNOMIAL MATHEMATICS
#Given a set of roots, it is possible to show the polynomial coefficients:
np.poly([-1, 1, 1, 10]) #which returns [1,-11,9,11,-10],i.e.x**4-11*x**3+9*x**2+11*x-10
#The opposite operation can be performed: given a set of coefficients, the root function returns all of the polynomial roots:
np.roots([1, 4, -2, 3]) #which outputs as array([-4.57974010+0.j , 0.28987005+0.75566815j, 0.28987005-0.75566815j])
#Coefficient arrays of polynomials can be integrated.By default, the constant is set to zero:
np.polyint([1, 1, 1, 1])  #outputs as array([ 0.25 , 0.33333333, 0.5 , 1. , 0. ])
#Similarly, derivatives can be taken:
np.polyder([1./4., 1./3., 1./2., 1., 0.])  #which outputs as array([ 1., 1., 1., 1.])
#The functions polyadd, polysub, polymul, and polydiv also handle proper addition, subtraction, multiplication,
#and division of polynomial coefficients, respectively.
#The function polyval evaluates a polynomial at a particular point. Consider x**3-2*x**2+2 evaluated at x=4 :
np.polyval([1, -2, 0, 2], 4)  #outputs 34
#Finally, the polyfit function can be used to fit a polynomial of specified order to a set of data using a least-squares approach:
x = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]
y = [0, 2, 1, 3, 7, 10, 11, 19]
np.polyfit(x, y, 2)   #which outputs as array([ 0.375 , -0.88690476, 1.05357143])..these are polynomial coefficients
#More sophisticated interpolation routines can be found in the SciPy package.


                                           # STATISTICS
#In addition to the mean, var, and std functions, NumPy supplies several other methods for returning statistical features of arrays.
a = np.array([1, 4, 3, 8, 9, 2, 3], float)
np.median(a)   #median is 3.0
#correlation coefficient
a = np.array([[1, 2, 1, 3], [5, 3, 1, 8]], float)
c = np.corrcoef(a)
#Similarly, the covariance for data can be found:
np.cov(a)


                                                #RANDOM NUMBERS
#NumPy uses a particular algorithm called the Mersenne Twister to generate pseudorandom numbers.The random number seed can be set:
np.random.seed(293423)    #if seed is not specified. NumPy automatically selects a different integer each time program is run
#An array of random numbers in the half-open interval [0.0, 1.0) can be generated:
np.random.rand(5) # outputs as array([ 0.40783762, 0.7550402 , 0.00919317, 0.01713451, 0.95299583])
#The rand function can be used to generate two-dimensional random arrays, or the resize function could be employed here:
np.random.rand(2,3)    #outputs as array([[ 0.50431753, 0.48272463, 0.45811345],
                             #              [ 0.18209476, 0.48631022, 0.49590404]])  #also np.random.rand(6).reshape((2,3))
#To generate a single random number in [0.0, 1.0),
np.random.random()
#To generate random integers in the range [min, max) use randint(min, max):
np.random.randint(5, 10)
#In each of these examples, we drew random numbers form a uniform distribution.
#NumPy also includes generators for many other distributions, including the Beta, binomial, chi-square
#Dirichlet, exponential, F, Gamma, geometric, Gumbel, hypergeometric, Laplace, logistic, log-
#normal, logarithmic, multinomial, multivariate, negative binomial, noncentral chi-square,
#noncentral F, normal, Pareto, Poisson, power, Rayleigh, Cauchy, student's t, triangular, von
#Mises, Wald, Weibull, and Zipf distributions. Here we only give examples for two of these.
#To draw from the discrete Poisson distribution with λ=6.0;
np.random.poisson(6.0)
#To draw from a continuous normal (Gaussian) distribution with mean and standard deviation :
np.random.normal(1.5, 4.0)
#To draw from a standard normal distribution (mean=0 ,sd=1 ), omit the arguments:
np.random.normal()
#To draw multiple values, use the optional size argument:
np.random.normal(size=5)
#The random module can also be used to randomly shuffle the order of items in a list.
#This is sometimes useful if we want to sort a list in random order:
l = range(10)
np.random.shuffle(l)












    







